Guide to the Ethel Hays collection M2142
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Ethel Hays collection
1923-1929
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hays, Ethel
Brinkley, Nell, 1886-1944
Wells, Carolyn, 1862-1942
M2142
2 Linear Feet (1 box, 1 flat box)
1920s comics by women artists clipped from local newspapers.
Scope and Contents
These 1920s comics and illustrations were clipped from local newspapers by an unknown person. The papers include the Redwood City Tribune, San Francisco News, San Francisco Examiner, and San Francisco Call, and a few from the Daily Palo Alto Times. Most comics are by Ethel Hays, but there a several illustrations by Nell Brinkley and a few other artists.
Ethel Hays (1892-1989) was a syndicated cartoonist known especially for her flapper-themed characters. She studied art with the intention of being a painter, but decided to pursue comics through correspondence courses with the Landon School of Illustration and Cartooning. In late 1923 the school's founder Charles Landon helped her get hired by the Cleveland Press, where she became a regular contributor with the Newspaper Enterprise Association (NEA) syndicate. Her first column had been named "Vic and Ethel" with writer Victoria Benham, but when Benham got married and quit, Hays continued on her own with a cartoon titled "Ethel," and a little later "Flapper Fanny Says." Her one-panel cartoons with lightly humorous social commentary and crisp, fashionable line drawings made her extremely popular, and over 500 papers carried her work within the first year of syndication. Hays later became an illustrator for children's books, especially Raggedy Ann and Andy, as well as coloring books and paper doll cut-out books.
Nell Brinkley (1886 – 1944) belongs to an older generation of illustrators, with her first published work illustrating a children's book in 1906. A native of Colorado, Brinkley also was hired to make drawings for The Denver Post and later the Rocky Mountain News. In 1907 she began working for Hearst at the New York Journal-American in New York and quickly rose to fame. Her iconic Brinkley Girl was a likely influence on Hays. Most of the newspaper illustrations present here are color full page illustrations in the American Weekly magazine section of San Francisco Examiner, and many are from two running series created with author Carolyn Wells.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was given to Stanford University, Special Collections at an unknown date.
Comic books, strips, etc.; Women cartoonists -- United States; Hays, Ethel; Brinkley, Nell, 1886-1944; Wells, Carolyn, 1862-1942
- 1. Ethel Hays
  - 1.1 Ethel
    Scope and Contents
    Most of Hays comics during this time were titled "Ethel," but some running themes were also titled "Then & Now" and "Goat Getters" or "Doesn't It Get Your Goat?" These are foldered separately but belong in the same chronological sequence as the other comics. There are also some comics from a small summer-themed series titled "A Summer Girl's Boys."
    - undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Goat Getters / Doesn't It Get Your Goat, 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Then & Now, 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - A Summer Girl's Boys, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Contains panels numbered 1-6 and 8.
  - 1.2 Flapper Fanny Says
    - undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1929 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1.3 Hays full page spreads, SF News, SF Chronicle, 2-12/1929 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1.4 Allene Summers, "Teaching Art to Uncle Sam's Wounded Veterans Started 'Ethel'" (NEA article, unknown newspaper), circa 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 2. Nell Brinkley
  - various (mostly full page), 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Adventures of Prudent Prim (Verses by Carolyn Wells, Drawings by Nell Brinkley), 1925-11-1926-02 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fortunes of Flossy (Verses by Carolyn Wells, Drawings by Nell Brinkley), 1926-12-1927-06 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 3. Other comics
  - Martin - Boots And Her Buddies (2 comics), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Dorothy Flack (2 comics), 1928 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fay King (one panel, torn into pieces) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous
  - cover, Life Magazine 8/23/1929 by Raymond Thayer; unknown magazine cover by Irving Einclair 6/1927 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Uncredited drawings (one signed "CR") (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Unrelated clippings (Box 1, Folder 17)